Guide to the Brooklyn Navy Yard oral history collection ARC.003
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Oral History Interview with Pearl Hill, February 20, 2007; 2010.003.034
  Work; Queens (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Welding; Shipbuilding |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Family life -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Shipfitting; Women |x Employment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Work environment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Shipyards |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Restaurants |z New York (State) |z New York; World War, 1939-1945; New York Naval Shipyard
- Oral History Interview with Mary Hogan and Anne Hannigan, July 28, 2008; 2010.003.014
  Mary Hannigan Hogan (1923- ) grew up in Park Slope, Brooklyn with five siblings. Hogan attended Manual Traning High School, now known John Jay High School. Shortly after graduating from high school, she began working at the Brooklyn Navy Yard as a welder and adding up costs for ship parts. Hogan married in 1944. After leaving the Navy Yard, she worked at various office jobs and moved with her family to Long Island, New York./n/nAnne Mastrion Hannigan (1922- ) grew up in Park Slope, Brooklyn near Mary Hogan. Anne Hannigan married Mary Hogan's brother, Johnny Hannigan, in 1944. Anne Hannigan also attended Manual Training High School, where she learned typing and stenography. Hannigan began work at the Navy Yard around the time of Mary Hogan, working as a lathe operator and reading blueprints to determine the number of parts needed. After leaving the Navy Yard, Anne Hannigan worked in the claims department of Pilgrim Laundry and later moved to Long Island, New York.
  The interview with Mary Hannigan Hogan (1923- ) and Anne Mastron Hannigan (1922) also includes their niece, Maureen Hawkins and Mary Hogan's daughter, Debbie Hogan Russ. The women discuss their upbringing in Brooklyn, getting jobs at the Navy Yard, commuting to work, safety issues, uniforms, salaries and marriage. While Mary Hogan began working as a welder and Anne Hannigan as a lathe operator, both women began doing office work shortly after they started. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan and Jennifer Egan.
  Blueprints; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Park Slope (New York, N.Y.); Family life -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Friendship; Irish Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Local transit -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Sailors; Security systems; Transportation -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Wages |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Women |x Employment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Work environment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Shipbuilding |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Shipyards |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Laundry industry |z New York (State) |z Kings County; World War, 1939-1945; New York Naval Shipyard; Hannigan, Anne Mastrion; Manual Training High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Missouri (Battleship: BB 63)
- Oral History Interview with Clarence Irving, September 26, 2008; 2010.003.039
  Clarence Irving (1924- ) grew up in New York and Washington, DC. His father worked in the Newport News shipyard. Irving moved from DC to New York to live with his brother and became a machinist at the Brooklyn Navy Yard.
  During his interview, Clarence Irving (1924- ) talks about his family and educational background before coming to work at the Navy Yard. He says that the best option at the time for African Americans was to work for the federal government because there was less discrimination and more protection for minority employees. He also talks about his work as a machinist, describing the facilities he worked in and the tools he used, as well as working conditions, yard safety, accidents and security. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
  Accidents; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Queens (New York, N.Y.); Washington (D.C.); African Americans; Baseball |z New York (State) |z New York; Family life -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Warships; Neighborhoods -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Race discrimination; Security systems; Shipbuilding |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Shipyards |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Work environment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; World War, 1939-1945; New York Naval Shipyard
- Oral History Interview with Richard Johnson and Geraldine Johnson, February 12, 2009; 2010.003.003
  Geraldine Kiernan Johnson (1925- ) was born in Norfolk, Virginia, but moved soon after to the Washington, D.C. area. As her father (James Eugene Kiernan) was a member of Governor General Frank Murphy's staff, the family lived in the Philippines from 1933-1936. Kiernan was transferred to the Brooklyn Navy Yard in 1940 after spending a few years at the Camden Navy Yard. In 1941 the family moved to join Kiernan in Brooklyn Navy Yard housing on Flushing Avenue. Geraldine Johnson attended the Packer Collegiate Institute. Richard Johnson (1919- ) grew up in Leominster, Massachusetts and Newark, New Jersey where he attended the Newark College of Engineering where he signed up to be an engineer for the Navy. He graduated in 1941. After college, Johnson went to the Navy Post-Graduate School in Annapolis, Maryland and then began work at the Brooklyn Navy Yard as a naval engineer and assistant hull superintendent. Geraldine and Richard Johnson were married in 1944 at the Officer's Club at the Brooklyn Navy Yard, after which they spent a few years in San Diego. At the time of the interview, the Johnsons were living in Connecticut.
  The interview with Richard (1919- ) and Geraldine Johnson (1925- ) focuses on Richard Johnson's work with the US Navy and the Brooklyn Navy Yard, as well as James Eugene Kiernan's work as a naval officer and a supervisor at the Brooklyn Navy Yard. The Johnsons talk about their family history and lives before they moved to Brooklyn. Geraldine Johnson describes her life growing up at the Brooklyn Navy Yard. Richard Johnson describes the layout and organization of the shipyard, his day to day activities, how materials were moved around the yard, wood storage, promotions within the US Navy, his education and the launch of the USS Missouri. Richard Johnson also describes books and other materials he has collected about the history of the Brooklyn Navy Yard. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan and Daniella Romano.
  Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); New Utrecht (New York, N.Y.); Park Slope (New York, N.Y.); Newark (N.J.); Cranes, derricks, etc; Dating (Social customs); Dry docks; Engineering; Engineering and construction; Italian Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Naval operations; Sailors; Security systems; Sex role; Shipbuilding |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Shipfitting; Shipyards |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Transportation -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Women |x Employment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Work environment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; New York Naval Shipyard; Johnson, Geraldine Kiernan; Packer Collegiate Institute; Bon Homme Richard (Aircraft carrier); Missouri (Battleship: BB 63); Iowa (Battleship)
- Oral History Interview with Veronica Kieffer, August 19, 1987; 1995.005.004
  Veronica Marino Kieffer (ca. 1920- ) worked at Sperry Gyroscope in Brooklyn with drill presses and gyroscopes. After Sperry moved to Long Island, Kieffer began working at the Navy Yard. While working at the Navy Yard, Kieffer lived in Sheepshead Bay.
  During her interview, Veronica Marino Kieffer discusses her relationships with the other workers and her supervisors, her work cleaning and repairing binoculars, her Italian background, her family and the work she did before coming to the Navy Yard. In one instance, Kieffer was sent home for not wearing her hat while working on a drill press because of the danger of getting het hair caught in the machine. Interview conducted by Benjamin Filene.
  Ethnicity; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Sheepshead Bay (New York, N.Y.); Friendship; Binoculars; Women |x Employment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Wages |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Shipyards |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Italian Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; World War, 1939-1945; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Emigration and immigration; Immigrants; New York Naval Shipyard; Kieffer, Veronica Marino; Sperry Gyroscope Company, inc
- Oral History Interview with Alfred Kolkin, July 15, 2008; 2010.003.015
  Alfred Kolkin (1918- ) grew up in Brooklyn, Manhattan and the Bronx. After graduating from high school, Kolkin worked for the Sperry Gyroscope Company in Downtown Brooklyn, after which he applied to be a mechanic at the Brooklyn Navy Yard, where he began working in 1940. He married his wife, Lucille Gerwitz Kolkin (who was interviewed in 1989 and has since passed away), shortly before enlisting in the army and moving to Chicago to receive special electronic training, and then to California, where Lucille Kolkin joined him.
  During his interview, Alfred Kolkin (1918- ) discusses his life growing up in New York and trying to find a job after graduating from high school during the Depression. At the Navy Yard, Kolkin worked as a machinist in Building 128, where he made ship parts and used a horizontal boring mill to finish the surfaces on castings for ship artillery. Later, he was promoted into a managerial position. During his time at the Navy Yard, Kolkin was also an editor of a local union newspaper. Kolkin joined the army in 1944, and relates his experience on a repair ship in the Pacific at the end of WWII, where he witnessed Japan surrendering aboard the USS Missouri. During the interview, he also speaks about his various jobs after the end of WWII, working in machine shops, a tool and dye factory and a printing factory. Kolkin discusses his union involvement, and the difficulties of getting by with a family during union strikes (something that his wife also discusses during her interview). Also present during the interview was Alfred and Lucille Kolkin's daughter, Judy Kaplan. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan and Jennifer Egan.
  Family; Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York; Navy-yards and naval stations; Shipbuilding |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Shipfitting; Shipyards |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Transportation -- New York (State) -- Kings County; World War, 1939-1945; New York Naval Shipyard; Kolkin, Alfred; Sperry Gyroscope Company, inc; Missouri (Battleship: BB 63)
- Oral History Interview with Lucille Kolkin, March 16, 1989; 1995.005.001
  Lucille Gerwitz Kolkin (1919-1997) grew up in Borough Park, Brooklyn and Bensonhurst, Brooklyn and attended Hunter College. She began working at the Brooklyn Navy Yard in 1941 or 1942 at the age of 23 as a tack welder. She remained at the Navy Yard for about 2 years before she moved to California after her husband went into service. Kolkin returned to New York to raise her children. At the time of the interview she was living in Long Island.
  n the interview, Lucille Gerwitz Kolkin (1919-1997) discusses the dangers and uncomfortable conditions she faced working as a welder, the camaraderie she felt with the other workers, her wages, her union involvement and her relationships with the other workers and her supervisors. She also describes the clothing she wore to work, vacations she took and her Jewish background. After leaving the Brooklyn Navy Yard, Kolkin talks about her experiences as a mother and wife, and about returning to work after her kids had grown up. Interview conducted by Diane Esses.
  Borough Park (New York, N.Y.); Bensonhurst (New York, N.Y.); Women |x Employment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Shipyards |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Shipbuilding |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Navy-yards and naval stations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jewish women; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Emigration and immigration; New York Naval Shipyard; Kolkin, Lucille Gewirtz
- Oral History Interview with Helen Kuhner, December 26, 2006; 2010.003.036
  Helen Kuhner (1918- ) grew up in Brooklyn in the Prospect Heights neighborhood. She lived in North Carolina working as a secretary at Fort Bragg when her husband went into service. After he shipped out, she came to live in Brooklyn with her mother and began working at the Brooklyn Navy Yard as a stenographer. Kuhner left the Navy Yard when her husband returned. The family moved to Staten Island and then Long Island. Kuhner now lives in Florida and has five grandchildren and six great grandchildren.
  In her interview, Helen Kuhner (1918- ) discusses her work as a stenographer at the Brooklyn Navy Yard and life as a mother during WWII while her husband was at war. She talks about interactions between men and women working at the Yard and how she dealt with the whistles and attention from the men. Kuhner tells a story about staying home sick and remembers someone from the Navy Yard coming to check and make sure she was at home. She also remembers a woman who would check the bathroom stalls to make sure workers were not smoking or resting while on the job. Her interview brings up working conditions for women, her Irish-American background, and being a working mother. Interview conducted by Jennifer Egan.
  Warships; Sands Street (New York, N.Y.); Fort Bragg (N.C.); Prospect Heights (New York, N.Y.); Family life -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Working mothers; Military spouses; Stenographers; World War, 1939-1945; Women |x Employment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; United States |x Armed Forces |x Civilian employees; Sex discrimination; Irish Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; New York Naval Shipyard
- Oral History Interview with Mildred Leipzig, September 16, 2009; 2010.003.016
  Mildred (Mimi) Levin Leipzig (1923- ) was born at the Brooklyn Jewish Hospital across the street from her father's pharmacy in Crown Heights, Brooklyn. Leipzig attended Girl's Commercial High School (now Prospect Heights High School). She began working at the Brooklyn Navy Yard in 1940 or 1941 shortly after marrying Arthur Leipzig, a photographer for the New York City newspaper PM. Mildred Leipzig left her job as an assistant shipfitter at the Navy Yard in 1942 when she had her first child.
  Mildred (Mimi) Levin Leipzig (1923- ) remembers many detailed stories about her childhood and life in Brooklyn, New York, as well as the experiences of her sisters and parents. She describes her and her two sisters helping her father at his pharmacy and tells stories about visiting the Brooklyn Children's Museum, the Botanic Garden and Prospect Park with her father and sisters. Leipzig discusses growing up in a Jewish family in an Italian Catholic neighborhood, where her father often distributed medicines for free to families who could not afford them. Leipzig took a mechanical aptitude test for the Navy Yard shortly after finishing high school, and began working as a shipfitter's assistant where her main job was as an arc welder. There, she recalls using an asbestos blanket while welding as protection from burns. She also discusses her unique role as a woman at the Navy Yard and that men were often uncomfortable doing the same work as the women. More specifically, she discusses issues with the women's bathroom in her shop and an instance when a woman offered to give her a skirt while she was on her way to work in her coveralls (implying that Leipzig was dressed inappropriately). Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
  Family; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Prospect Park (New York, N.Y.); Italian Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jewish women; Local transit -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Photographers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Religion and culture; Sex role; Shipbuilding |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Shipfitting; Transportation; Wages |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Welding; Women |x Employment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Work environment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; World War, 1939-1945; New York Naval Shipyard; Leipzig, Arthur; Brooklyn Children's Museum
- Oral History Interview with Sidonia Levine, November 18, 2006; 2010.003.035
  Sidonia Kessler Levine (1919- ) began working at the Brooklyn Navy Yard in November of 1942. She worked as a mechanic helper and shipfitter in Building 4 while her husband was deployed. Levine currently lives in Florida.
  In this interview, Sidonia Kessler Levine (1919- ) talks about how she came to work at the Brooklyn Navy Yard after spending some time at Western Electric. She mentions that she did very well on the Navy Yard test, on which she received the 15th best score out of 500 participants. While at the Navy Yard, Levine had her picture taken for the Shipworker and did an interview with the Brooklyn Eagle. She talks a lot about the camaraderie in the yard and the lasting friendships she made with the women she worked with in Building 4. She also details her job where she converted blueprints into wooden templates and attended extra school at Pratt for blueprint reading. She made her work uniform herself. Levine describes her visit to the Navy Yard in the 1990s as "sterile" compared to the liveliness of the atmosphere while she worked there. Interview conducted by Jennifer Egan.
  Warships; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Shipbuilding |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Family life -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Shipfitting; Blueprints; Friendship; Mechanics (Persons); Baseball players |z United States; World War, 1939-1945; Women |x Employment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jews, American |z New York (State) |z Kings County; New York Naval Shipyard
- Oral History Interview with Audrey Lyons, May 2, 2009; 2010.003.017
  Audrey Garbers Lyons (1924- ) grew up in the Cyprus Hills neighborhood of Brooklyn. Lyons attended Brooklyn College before she left to work at the Navy Yard in 1943 to help support her family after her father's business closed. Unlike some of the other workers at the Navy Yard, Lyons was a federal employee.
  Audrey Garbers Lyons (1924- ) worked as a parts inspector at the Navy Yard for the federal government from 1943 until WWII ended in 1945. Lyons used a micrometer to measure ship parts. During her interview, she remembers that the women mostly tested the smaller parts. She also recalls talking and singing with the women she worked with, who were mostly college educated, and many of whom were married and worried about their husbands in the War. Lyons described her section of the Navy Yard as a little village, explaining that she recognized everyone in her own building, but no one else at the Navy Yard. She also remembers the christening of the USS Missouri, smells from a nearby chocolate factory and the jumpsuit she wore at work. Also present at the time of the interview was Susan Lyons, Audrey Lyons' daughter. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan and Jennifer Egan.
  Family; Cypress Hills (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Friendship; Local transit; Neighborhoods -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Shipbuilding |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Shipfitting; Transportation; Wages |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Women |x Employment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Work environment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; World War, 1939-1945; New York Naval Shipyard; Missouri (Battleship: BB 63)
- Oral History Interview with George Martinez, June 24, 2008; 2010.003.018
  George Martinez (1933- ) grew up in Williamsburg, Brooklyn with two sisters. His parents were both born in Columbia, as well as his older sister Grace Martinez De La Rosa (1923- ), who worked as a welder at the Brooklyn Navy Yard during WWII. After marrying, Grace Martinez De La Rosa moved to Mexico City, while George Martinez worked for the US Postal Service and currently lives on Long Island. Grace Martinez De La Rosa (1923- ) was studying to become a teacher in college when WWII began and she left to work at the Navy Yard.
  In his interview, George Martinez (1933- ) discusses his own experience growing up during the war, as well as what he remembers of his sister's work as a welder at the Navy Yard. He remembers collecting scraps for the war effort and his sister returning home with a burned uniform or eye injuries. George Martinez explains that many people who could not get jobs before the war, because of disabilities or race, were able to get jobs at the Navy Yard during this time. He also recalls the block party with his neighbors to celebrate the end of the war. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
  Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Williamsburg (New York, N.Y.); Long Island (N.Y.); Mexico; Family; Neighborhoods -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Shipbuilding |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Shipfitting; Shipyards |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Wages |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Women |x Employment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Work environment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Emigration and immigration; World War, 1939-1945; New York Naval Shipyard; De La Rosa, Grace Martinez
- Oral History Interview with Antoinette Mauro, July 31, 2006; 2010.003.037
  Antoinette Irrera Mauro (ca. 1925- ) began working at the Brooklyn Navy Yard just after she finished high school at the age of 18. She worked as a draughtswoman from 1943 until she was laid off just a few weeks after the war ended in 1945. Mauro was called back in 1947 and again in 1950. Her husband (Louis Mauro) worked at the Navy Yard after he came back from the War with blueprints and then in the technical library until the yard was decommissioned. Mauro left in 1951 when she was pregnant with her son.
  In her interview, Antoinette Irrera Mauro (ca. 1925- ) details the work she did as a draughtswoman in the electrical department at the Brooklyn Navy Yard. She emphasizes how nice her coworkers were, even though there were only two women working in her department of 27 workers. Mauro started working in Building 3 and later in Building 77 when her department was moved. She also discusses her commute, Yard security, friendships with coworkers and watching various ship launchings. Interview conducted by Jennifer Egan.
  Warships; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Blueprints; Work environment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Security systems; Women |x Employment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Draft |z New York (State) |z New York; World War, 1939-1945; New York Naval Shipyard; Missouri (Battleship: BB 63)
- Oral History Interview with William Obitz, May 18, 2009; 2010.003.045
  William Obitz (1926-) was born in Plymouth, Pennsylvania. He grew up on a farm about 10 miles outside of Plymouth, PA. His father worked in the coal mines for approximately thirty years. Obitz enlisted in the Navy in 1943 and completed boot camp at Sampson, New York. He worked as a mess cook, gunner and deckhand on the USS Missouri out of the Brooklyn Navy Yard. After his work in the Navy, Obitz worked as a welder in New Jersey for twenty-two years.
  In this interview, Obitz primarily discusses his experiences aboard the USS Missouri, where he was a deckhand, mess cook and gunner from 1944 through the end of World War II. While on the Missouri, he witnessed a kamikaze plane attack. Other topics covered include his upbringing on a Pennsylvania farm; his enlistment and training in the Navy; his time at the Brooklyn Navy Yard preparing the Missouri for deployment; and how he met his wife. Interview conducted at the U.S.S. Missouri Reunion in Virginia on May 18, 2009. Interview conducted by Daniella Romano.